How you talk indicates to people how you are. Beware of revealing a personality
that you don't have. There is no absolute right or wrong in regard to intonation
because a case can be made for stressing just about any word or syllable, but you
actually reveal a lot about yourself by the elements you choose to emphasize. For
example, if you say, hello, this intonation would indicate doubt. You say
hello when answering the phone because you don't know who's on the other end. Or when
you go into a house and you don't know who's there because you don't see anyone.
But if you're giving a speech or making a presentation and you stand up in front of
a crowd and say hello, the people would probably laugh because it sounds so
uncertain. This is where you'd confidently want to say hello, my name is so-and-so. A
second example is my name is as opposed to my name is. It sounds as if you're going
to continue with more personal information. My name is so-and-so, my
address is such-and-such, my blood type is O. Since it may not be your intention to
give all that information, stay with the standard, hello, my name is so-and-so. If
you stress I every time, it will seem that you have a very high opinion of yourself.
Try it. I'm taking American accent training. I've been paying attention to
pitch, too. I think I'm quite wonderful. An earnest, hard-working person might
emphasize words this way. I'm taking American accent training. Can I learn this
stuff? I hope to make it as enjoyable as possible. I'll force myself to enjoy it if
I have to, although the only way to get it is to practice all the time, 24 hours a
day. A doubting Thomas would show up with, I should pick up on the
American intonation pattern pretty easily, but it looks pretty hard, too.
I've been talking to a lot of Americans lately, and they tell me that I'm easier
to understand, but I think they're just being polite.